A major earthquake shook
the Caribbean nation of Haiti late today.
It hit just 14 miles
from the capital city Port-au-Prince.
The U.S. Geological Survey
reported a magnitude of 7.0,
the largest ever
recorded in that region.
Reports said the presidential
palace and a hospital collapsed
along with other buildings.
The president
and his wife escaped injury,
but thousands of other people
were killed or buried under rubble.
Magnitude 7.0 is the very
major quake and this one was shallow
and of course, you've noted
near a very large population center.
So we have,
unfortunately, the feeling
that this is going to be
a very devastating event.
It’s half day
right now, it's a dark mo...
I think it's one of
the darkest moments we've ever faced.
I was at home.
My house is built of wood.
and suddenly
is started shaking, very strongly.
I lay down and my children did too.
We all lay down on the floor.
It was only after the earthquake
that we got up.
I went outside and I saw
houses broken down to pieces,
many people had died
and I started to scream, very loudly
"Oh my God
what is happening?
What is this?"
I have never seen anything like it
before in my life.
Then I went to my neighbours'
to help them free people
who got stuck under debris
We were celebrating Eucharist
that's when I felt earth movements.
Earth started to move and I have said
to the priest "Shall we go back home?
I have a feeling something bad
is going to happen."
So we went back to this place
and we just watched
the house, the school, without moving.
Luckily, we didn't stay inside,
we had time to get out and escape death.
There were people saying
"The end of the world is coming"
It was the first time
we have found ourselves
in a situation like this.
We didn't know this.
We have never seen an earthquake on Haiti,
this was the first.
People said: "The God has returned,
it is the day of reckoning."
Sometimes the nets are empty, and
the next day we catch four hundred fish.
I get 800-100 Haiti Dollars
for that.
We keep some
and sell the rest.
Sometimes it takes just an hour
to pull up the fishing net,
but often you will need four hours.
It is a hard work,
and it takes time.
It is unpredictable too.
Sometimes you catch a lot fish,
that's great.
But you can also spend days,
with net set deep and still get nothing.
But when you catch something you can sell,
it provides some means of livelihood.
When I am doing good,
I can make 400-500
haitian dollars a day.
It was my uncle who introduced me to
the craft, he taught me how to catch fish.
Nowadays when I am on my own, I learned
much more and I am more experienced.
I also trained to be a bricklayer,
to help with constructions.
When I am not out on the sea,
I work as a construction worker,
to earn a living.
There are days when the sea is rough,
then it's hard, we have no work.
That's why I work on constructions.
It is not easy to be a fisherman,
on Haiti.
Life on Haiti is hard.
To take care of oneself and a family.
When I am on the sea, I work hard.
I am here every day.
I sail the sea every single day.
Sometimes I catch fish,
sometimes nothing at all.
Here in Baie de Henne
the sea is everything we have.
Without working on the sea,
we have nothing to do,
and we have nothing.
When the nets are empty,
or the fish is no good to eat.
we have to go out again and again.
A while back we have had a rough time
due to the weather.
We are still sorting out the mess,
it caused us great damages.
Republic of Haiti
is one of the Great Antilles islands.
After Dominican Republic and Cuba,
it is the third largest
country in the Caribbean Sea.
Haiti, is considered to be the poorest
country in the western hemisphere.
The journey
to this unfortunate primacy
through a bloody history
and a series of misfortunes,
led Haitians on the very edge
of the civilized world.
As early as 5000 years ago
the island was inhabited
by the indigenous people of Taínos.
Their simple and peacefull existince
in the tropical paradise
was disrupted when a ship named Santa María
run aground on the Northern
part of the island in 1492.
Christopher Columbus,
who in his early journeys
had only anchored in the Bahamas and Cuba
named the island Hispaniola.
As the name suggests,
it then belonged to the Spanish crown.
Following a friendly welcome,
he left there a part of his crew
and founded the first settlement
in the new found world.
We distribute
milk before the school starts every day.
This is a project
that we got from Aries, France.
The use of this milk is
very very important for this place
because many
of our children come to school
without eating or drinking
and earlier what is to
happen is to have children,
who is to faint fall in the class,
even during assembly.
And this is what made us look
for a project that will help our children.
Since two yers we are
distributing milk for the children
and since we start to
distributing milk, we never had any case of
children falling,
fainting and things like that.
Otherwise, many used to
come and say, I have stomach aches.
Actually, it is not a
stomach ache, it is hunger.
So this is a problem
that we are trying to solve
to a great extent by helping
these children have this cup of milk.
There are some who don't want it,
but most majority
of the children have it in the morning.
Some want a little bit, someone more.
According to their need, according
to their desire saw milk in the school.
Since 2006
I have been visting this place
and I have seen many children,
that were not in school.
With the permission of our mother superior,
I requested
to open a small school for poor children.
A convent used to be here
between 2004 - 2010.
But the earthquake had come
that destroyed everything.
Both the house of the
sisters and the school.
We couldn't stay in the ruins after the
earthquake, with all the young people.
We have seven young sister
that accompanied us outside.
Every night
we used to go to vacant land nearby
and we spent the night together
with other people
from demolished places.
We stayed there for 2 weeks
and in the end we decided
to built tents in this yard.
Between 2010 and 2013,
we had a small housing
and the main tent here.
And our friendly organization
help us find charity supporters,
that have built this community.
Caritas Slovakia
visited us
and then heled us build
four classrooms and restroom facilities
to accommodate all the children.
Since that
the school works perfectly
We now have 495 students,
children in the preschool,
and elementary school.
and we hope that we will continue
in the philoshy of this community.
A girraffe...
who will show me a girraffe?
What does a girraffe look like?
Correct!!!
And who will show me a lion?
Hello,
dear children and dear teachers,
We are very happy,
that can visit you
this year.
It is with our great pleasure
to be here with you and the sisters
in the school of St. Jospeh.
We bring many greetings
from Caritas Czech Republic.
We hope that
you will do well this school year.
and have a great success,
beacause you
are the future of this land.
We pray for you and wish you
let the good protect you.
Thank you very much and enjoy your day.
Thank you.
Continual colonization ment a distaster
for the natives.
Their exploitation
used especially to discover gold.
Together with european diseases.
Causing that in just 40 years
the natives had become extinct.
The natives, as the workforce
were soon replaced
by the brought african slaves.
While the colonists
in the pursue for gold on the
American soil had started to leave,
French pirates started
to settle on the island.
A small isle
had become their shelther
by the northern coast.
named Tortuga.
The main role of the priest
is to help people with findinng God
a to meet with the Christ
through his Word.
It doesn't mean
just to deliver the Word.
but also to help them grow.
So apart the pastoral mission I have,
in this parish,
I also have a social mission.
I also help people
to improve their living standards.
When you look at the houses,
they are old houses,
as in the times of slaves and natives.
There is no sufficient infrastruscture
and the state level.
The government is almost non present.
Let me go back to Baie-de-Henne,
there are many children,
that can't go to school.
But those who have the luck,
will then stay home and leave the school.
Why?
Beacuse they don't have money.
I often go fishing,
I fish with my brother Wedline
to earn something extra
you understand?
Because my parents
don't have enough money
so I am trying to help them this way.
Everytime we have a holiday,
we try to help as we can,
so we go fishing.
Be standing in the corner
that is nothing for me.
Nothing for me.
Whe the school term allows to,
we work.
And when the holiday is over,
we go back to school.
So it is you,
that help this school to most
and I think it is you with the
support of people in Czech Republic
can help our young grow.
The Substitue Family Care Project
for me
is very unique.
It gave me a lot of hope.
You've become partners for me,
and helped me be diligiten
in my studies
get better
and do the best I can
and can excel in school.
Everytime,
when the school terms come,
I am happy.
I think about my god mother,
that sends me money,
so I can my books
and pay for studies for the term.
It was awesome
and it helped me very much.
Dear godmother,
I send you greetings my Grandmother,
I am thankful, that I can write this letter
to you.
Tell me what's new,
how are you, what do you do
and how is your health?
Everything is great here,
thanks God.
How is your family?
I'd like to thank you,
for everything you keep sending me.
I'd like to become a diplomat.
I love you very much.
Thanks for the wonderful presents.
Your God-doughter, Desilise Viola,
sending you hugs and wishes
for great success.
From Desilise Violdy to the Godmother.
Baei-de-Henne
Do you know, why children leave
the school of St. Maria Goretti?
Because they have difficulty
keeping up in school,
because they don't work enough.
Every children that leaves
the school of St. Maria Goretti,
are excluded from the Substitue family
care program,
and can't return.
Do you see?
Because children
that have not tried enough, and lost
the option of being in the programe,
did not appreciate that your sponsor,
must make a significant efforts
within the programme
to be able to pay for the school
they have to be modest at home.
It is a great chance,
for you in the program.
When you don't try enough,
you lose the chance for a better life.
You have to study
to have good grades
a can stay
both in the programe,
and the school of St. Maria Goretti.
To work with children
is a pleasure and joy.
I live for them.
I stay with them
especially every night,
when we prepare to sleep.
I tell them jokes
before they go sleep.
I love children, I live with them.
Everytime I leave home,
when I know I will see them
it is a happines, a pure happiness.
Their hugs.
Children love teachers.
They don't always have father at home,
Nemají vždycky doma tatínky,
but when they feel the presence of a man,
it helps them experience they have one.
It is a luck being with the children.
But we have people,
that want to move, leave the country.
That is a problem.
But when we do something
that we love,
we don't have problems.
We feel good
and feel success,
perfect happiness.
Especially with the children.
When we prepare some activities
with the students,
we see children dance,
sing, recite poetry and so.
It is wonderful.
If we had an auditorium,
where children could perform
that could be a great thing
for the community,
the faith could spread there
through the education or
cultural activities.
We also now,
that our children become adults
and will contributing
in the future of this country.
We will see,
had the chance to be a part of
their growing up.
It's wort it.
We often bring bad news about Haiti
to the world
and a bad image,
but there are good things on Haiti.
Our situation can
often be seen as bad
in the media,
but there good things here.
There are also
that enjoy their work,
that like to welcome guests.
We can't just accept
what is said, what we hear
on the radio or in the television.
but we also need experience
with loving a neighbour.
especially the people
of Baie-de-Henne.
Haiti is not only
and poverty and suffering.
Come visit us,
so you can discover
a taste Haiti, experience the
love of people in Baie-de-Henne,
that always have their smile,
character
and love to all people of goodwill.
Everyone is after me.
We are here with the dudes
The sunset is absolutely epic.
The others are on the beach.
...
Three, two, one..
The growing influx
of French settlers.
on the western half of the island,
culminated with the end of 17th century
in division of the Hispaniola
into two parts.
Unlike the eastern, Spanish half
the French one experienced
an unseen growth.
the sugar cane platnations,
helped the Saint-Domingue,
become the richest French colony.
It went in hand with
increasing use of slave work
and rapidly growing
slave trade
from many places in Africa.
By the end of the 18th century,
The half of a milion
of slaves brought from Africa,
make up 90% of the population
on the island.
Next to the the most populous,
enslaved group of inhabitant,
lived a rich white class
of so called the big whites,
not so rich class of small whites,
then mulattos
mulatů
and also freed or redeemed slaves.
Food for the Poor
is an organization that helps
a lot of other
small organizations in Haiti.
When we have
a program, if we need something,
we can always ask them
and usually they provide us
with what they have.
2017... 2017?
2017...
We got a lot of medicine,
both most of them have an experation
in only one or two months.
We can't use them all in that time.
We use some during a week
but the rest stays with the nurses.
They can give it to other people
but it is all to be expired within a month.
So it's like instant coffee.
You get instant medicine,
which cannot be used after.
I volunteered to come to Haiti
because I had known the mission of Haiti
well earlier,
I had been responsible for the projects,
construction projects here
and I had worked on every year almost.
I had visited Haiti.
There was a deep longing within me
to live here,
to be with the people, because I felt
there was a greater need
where I could make myself useful.
For me what I would say is...
It's very difficult
to explain what Haiti is.
You need to come
and experience it yourselves
because the situation
here, if you are living in Europe,
you cannot
imagine the lives of people here
because they are some 50 years
backward, 100 years, I would say backward.
Well, most of the
people speak about Haiti
they speak about the rich people.
They did speak about wealth
you see TV, television
programs, all beautiful places
where there
are big hotels and the beaches.
Where rich people are.
But this forgotten poor people,
nobody shows them in the television. No.
You don't see any programs
of this, but there are lots of the people
whom we serve here in the center
are theforgotten
people of Haiti I would say.
They have no houses,
there are no jobs.
They are ready
to come to the center for nutrition
and you see from morning, 9:00
till 12:00, they'll sit to get that food.
It is food that matters for them
and it's a pathetic condition
it's terrible,
but yet we need to support them
we need to stand by them.
This is a house
where we have rented it.
We have rented
one room for this family.
You can come and see the family.
Have a look at the house.
You see the houses
around here all houses around
there are quite a number of houses
that we have built here in this village
with the help of
the money that charitas Olomouc
given us also
and this is a big need here
because there are
lots of people who are homeless.
They don't have houses.
So therefore,
this has helped us a lot
to help these people.
It is because this is a quite
poor area.
that's why we organizujeme
this medical camp
every year, for the children
of the St. Maria Goretti school.
So therefore
we tried to do what we can for
this group of
people who are with us,
this type
of people who are with us.
There are people who are well-to-do
who are in the town.
They send their
children to better schools.
But as children
who cannot afford to go to schools
they come here to our school.
And we try to get
some help from other organizations
and to run the school
for the benefit
of all these poor people.
Quite social tension
and the resentment of slaves
soon stirred up
events in the continental France.
Conflicits between population groups
on the island
driven by the idea of the
Great French Revolution
benefited to the group of enslaved,
who rebelled in 1791
a achieved
the most successful slave rebellion.
on the american continent.
Their leader,
Toussaint Loverture
successfully fought
against local populations of
Spanish and English people
and suprisingly
also against mulattos.
Altough he did not succeed
against the Emperor Napoleon,
who won back
the rebelled colony,
his successors
in the end managed to
drive French out of the island,
vyvraždit zbylé
bělošské obyvatelstvo
and declare the Republic of Haiti
in 1804.
The work I do,
I took it over my father,
who brought me in,
before he died.
When he passed away,
I took over the job.
I build coffins,
used for transport to the chapel,
which is across here,
and for burrial on the cemetery.
a pro uložení na hřbitově.
The first contract I had,
was a coffion for a ten
year old child.
That was a though experience
right in the beginning.
When everything goes well,
every week,
we can complete four coffins.
But you know,
as the time goes,
we modernize the process.
So to built a single coffin
takes us less and less time.
I don't work for people
from the big cities,
they pay up to 500-100
Haitian gourde
(3,65 - 7,30 USD)
Here, I get around 30
Haitian gourde. (0,22 USD)
I don't get away with much here.
Making a livelihood with this craft
used to be much easier,
but now..
People want to work,
but there is no work.
Growing plants takes long,
we don't see much rain here.
It is a big, a really big problem.
Everything is expensive
for people
and they push prices down.
That's how it is around here.
When there is nothing
there is no action.
No action.
We take it as it is.
There is not..
There is not much we can do.
Nothing we can do.
Haiti became the first non-African
African-descendant state,
but for the next hundred years,
it was plagued by internal unrest
and political instability,
poverty, destitution, illiteracy,
and isolation.
Over a century of chaos was temporarily
ended by intervention of the United States.
Although the twenty-year occupation
primarily protected American interests,
it brought about various
advances in civilization and efforts
to define the Haitian identity.
Transportation is diffictult on Haiti.
The traffic is heavy,
and we don't have proper roads.
It's really tough.
But I drive anyway..
I do my best.
People over here are terrible drivers.
Some drive in the right lane,
others on the left side.
Everyone should be
driving in the right lane.
This brings trouble, many troubles.
We have a lot of car crashes,
many fatal too.
There is no police,
to watch over the traffic
on Haiti.
People just drive as they want.
To make a some money,
I drive people from one place
to another.
From one to another and back.
I am also a mechanic,
but that requires
many tools.
And I don't have a workshop.
I have no...
no place where I could work.
That's just..
life on Haiti.
I can't do my work...
without tools.
And I don't even
have enough customers.
There are no customers.
I am doing so-so.
When we left the airport..
it was just dirt and dust...
people selling fruits and vegetables,
on the streets..
oh and traffic jams.
Traffic jams that are a daily
routine here in the capital.
when you need to travel somewhere,
you usually spend the whole day in jams,
There are no traffic rules.
It is interesting,
on Haiti signs don't show the distance
but the time of travel.
We are now in Môle-Saint-Nicolas
This village is called Môle-Saint-Nicolas
and it was here
that people first set foot on our land.
When Christopher Columbus
searched for spices
he had discovered a new land,
that is now called Haiti.
When they landed,
their crew camped here
and founded a stronghold.
This place is full of traces
of Christopher Columbus.
Around 2012,
I met with my friend Julien,
he wanted to take up kitesurfing.
in the Dominican Republic.
I went into it with him.
Finally he brought me to this place.
It was my goal to return to Haiti,
work here and promote kitesurfing.
It was perfect for me.
I hope to help promote and develop
kitesurfing on Haiti in future.
It is big attraction for people
who come from different countries.
Not for those who live here.
I'd like to see more people,
maybe Europeans,
to come here and discover
beautiful beaches,
this wonderful country
that we have here.
It is just great to visit
and enjoy some adventure.
This palm,
that Stenley planted himself.
His gardening accomplishment.
I am planting my coconut tree
It takes around 10 year,
but when it grows,
I have my palm here on Haiti,
so I can just stop by here,
eat my coconuts.
So after the coconuts,
we now have sticky fingers from sugar cane.
Shall we have some more sugar cane?
After the Americans left in 1934, the
country returned to political instability.
The succession of dictators ended in 1957
with one - François Duvalier.
The rural doctor known as Papa Doc ruled
through a violent and repressive regime
and further deepened the
endless spiral of Haitian poverty.
of social disparities and deliberately
disrupted social bonds and solidarity.
After the revolution in 1986
that overthrew his successor-son,
the carousel of unrest
spun again,
with violent coups and
military dictatorships.
And if the unstable political situation
is combined with trembeling earth
as in the case of the
catastrophic 2010 earthquake,
which claimed the lives of several
hundred thousand people,
the escape from the vicious cycle
of poverty and the country's
dependency on humanitarian aid
becomes even more distant.
If..
I am to...
compare
life on Haiti
and in Czech Republic
is a totally,
a completely different life.
I think in Czech Republic
there are roads built
In Czech Republic
there are big
supermarkets,
big
businesses.
Large factories,
big economists,
that do their work.
There are also..
people,
with resources.
They build
houses and created
work places,
so people of Czech Republic can work.
Young people in Czech Republic
have it much easier to find work.
They have food,
they have drinking water.
They have everything
that we need.
On Haiti
we don't have much.
No roads,
no electricity,
we don't have
supermarkets.
We don't have
large companies.
We don't have companies
to give us a job.
But Haiti is my home
and I love my country.
There are many interesting places to visit.
We have our nature,
it is really wonderful.
Tourists that come to Haiti,
they don't want to go back home,
beacuse it's so lovely here.
We are beginning,
but our country is poor.
We don't have enough natural resources.
We don't even have
proper agriculture.
We have no work.
98% of people on Haiti
have no job.
We have 60 % students,
that finished the secondary school,
but can't continue to university.
We have..
we have..
students,
that have finished secondary education,
but have nothing to do.
And they leave the country
they go to Chile,
Dominican Republic
or Brasil.
They go to foreign countries
to escape the poverty,
because on Haiti...
there is nothing to live on.
But I stay here,
because I love my country.
Haiti is a wonderful contry.
It is my country, my motherland.
It is a country of my father,
my mother
and mine too.
And I love it.
But there many things,
that need to change.
(Czech verb conjugation)
I drink.
You drink.
They drink.
We drink...
we drink.
You drink.
They drink.
That's it.
Thank you very much!